Guide to the William S. Reese Collection of Robert Graves
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William S. Reese Collection of Robert Graves
1916-1987
1920-1980
GEN MSS 1137
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.89
(10 boxes)
Reese, William S., 1955-
Graves, Robert, 1895-1985
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William S. Reese (Yale 1977), 2002 and 2015; and purchased from William S. Reese on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002-2010.
Robert Graves (1895-1985)
Robert Graves, English poet and author.
William S. Reese (1955-)
William S. Reese (Yale 1977), rare book and manuscript collector and vendor; founded the William Reese Company, New Haven, Connecticut, in 1975.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: September and November 2002 Acquisitions; September 2002 Acquisition Addition; March 2010 Acquisition; and Other Acquisitions.
Scope and Contents
Papers relating to English author Robert Graves and his literary and social circle, collected by William S. Reese. The papers contain correspondence, 1916-1987 and undated, most autograph letters, signed, from Graves to correspondents including Desmond Flower, Dorothy and Ward Hutchinson, Violet and Walter McCormack, W. S. Merwin, Albert R. Mills, Frank Sanders, Siegfried Sassoon, Martin Secker, and other literary colleagues, friends, and family, with third-party correspondence about Graves, including letters from Beryl Graves, Siegfried Sassoon, and Laura (Riding) Jackson; autograph manuscript poems, 1920s-1960s; drafts, proofs, and correspondence relating to his novel An Ancient Castle, 1980-1981; a galley proof for Old Soldier Sahib, a memoir by Frank Richards, 1936; photographs of Graves, 1917-1934 and undated; a watercolor caricature of Graves by Sassoon, 1926; other correspondence and ephemera removed from books owned or inscribed by Graves, 1920s-1930s and undated; a storage box owned by a literary agent of Graves, undated; and exhibit labels for "Robert Graves: A Centennial Exhibition," curated by Reese at the Grolier Club, 1995.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Book collectors -- United States; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, English; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Photographs -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Storage boxes -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th Century; Flower, Desmond, 1907-1997; Graves, Beryl; Graves, Robert, 1895-1985; Hutchinson, Dorothy, active 1936-1972; Hutchinson, Ward; Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1901-1991; MacCormack, Violet; MacCormack, Walter; Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley), 1927-; Mills, Albert R.; Reese, William S., 1955-; Richards, Frank, 1883-1961; Sanders, Frank, active 1929-1963; Sassoon, Siegfried, 1886-1967; Secker, Martin, 1882-1978
- September and November 2002 Acquisitions, 1916-1987, undated; 0.84; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers
  - Correspondence
    Scope and Contents
    Autograph letters, signed, from Graves, unless otherwise noted
    - Anderson, Wallace L. (to Graves, with draft reply), 1948 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Begnal, [Michael H.?], 1972 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bleiler, E. F. (Everett Franklin), [1951] March 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Blunden, Edmund (from J. C. Dunn), 1929 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      About Blunden's Undertones and Graves's Good-bye to all that
      Accompanied by clippings about Graves
    - Cape, Jonathan, [1927] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      About T. E. Lawrence
    - Cassell & Company, [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Columbia Records, Inc. (contract for poetry readings), 1965 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cresswell, Mr., [1946] June 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Diefenbach, Larry, 1971 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Edwards, Ralph, no year February 10 and undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Flower, Desmond, 1938-1960, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      Includes related letters to Norman Flower and others
      Includes draft publicity blurbs, with autograph manuscript annotations by Graves, for The Anger of Achilles, with letter from T. R. Nicholson, of Cassell & Company; The Penny Fiddle; and Seven Days in New Crete
    - Garber, Howard J. (from Beryl Graves), 1977 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Garnett, David, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Graves, Amalie von Ranke, 1943 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      On verso: The Reader Over Your Shoulder, typescript fragment
    - Graves, John (to Graves's nephew, from Siegfried Sassoon), 1947 August (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Graves, Richard, 1958 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Greenleaf, Sheila, 1961 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Harrisson, Hilda, 1922 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Heppinstall, Rayner, 1947 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hutchinson, Dorothy and Ward, 1943-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Hutchinson, Dorothy and Ward (from Beryl Graves), [1942] April 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hutchinson, Dorothy and Ward (from Laura (Riding) Jackson), 1936-1940; 2 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
      With autograph manuscript notes by Ward Hutchinson
    - Judson, Mr., [1924?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Karlen, Arno (from John Cushman), 1963 November (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Correspondence between Karlen, assistant editor for an anthology, and Cushman, literary agent for Graves, about Graves's essay "Why Read Poetry?"
    - Keary, Jacquita, 1966-1972, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Landstrom, Mr., 1943 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Declining to speak "off record" about the post-war world
    - Lawrence, Seymour, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lind, L. R., 1948 June-August (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - McCormack, Jennifer, 1942-1965 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - McCormack, Violet and Walter, 1936-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - McCormack, Violet and Walter (from Laura (Riding) Jackson), 1935-1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Mathewson, Mr., 1922 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Maxon, C. M., 1957 October 23 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley) and Dorothy, 1951, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Mills, Albert R. (The Old Curiosity Shop), 1937-1940, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - Mills, Albert R. (The Old Curiosity Shop) (from Laura (Riding) Jackson), 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Mills, Albert R. (The Old Curiosity Shop) (from Ward Hutchinson, Dorothy Simmons, and Montague Simmons), 1938-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Montgomery, John, 1934 October 21 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Murray, Mary, 1922 February 6 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Orlandini, Edward, 1957 September (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Owen, Ben Evan, 1965, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Parker, Kenneth, 1962 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Pereira, H. P. E., 1941 February 7 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      About Sergeant Lamb of the Ninth
    - Pinker, Eric (from Martin Secker), 1919 July 28 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      From Graves's publisher to his literary agent about Country Sentiment
    - Powys-Evans, Mr., 1921, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      About a caricature and a visit by Powys-Evans to Oxford
    - Reese, William S. (from Laura (Riding) Jackson and Ted Wilentz), 1987 July (Box 3, Folder 50)
      About "vulgar errors" in cataloging Graves material
    - Roberts, Mr., [1940] (Box 3, Folder 51)
      Volunteering for national service
    - Roberts, Philip, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Sanders, Frank, 1929-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Includes letter, dated 1929, about Laura (Riding) Jackson
    - Sanders, Frank (from Laura (Riding) Jackson), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      Draft agreement to sell Graves's copy of The Seven Pillars of Wisdom, and receipt for payment by Sanders
    - Sassoon, Siegfried, 1916-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
      Includes "Escape" (poem), two drafts, with pen-and-ink illustrations
    - Saunders, Geoffrey, 1957 September 31 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      With poems
    - Saunders, Sally, 1963 January 6 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Secker, Martin, [1920] March 26 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Sitwell, Sacheverell (from Siegfried Sassoon), 1930 January 10 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Expressing his disgust for Good-bye to All That, and warning it is "lucky for [Graves] that he is in Spain"
      With two drawings, including one drawing of Sassoon punching Graves on the nose
    - Snodgrass, Mr., [1944] (Box 3, Folder 60)
      On verso: The Golden Fleece, typescript fragment
    - Spectorsky, A. C. (Auguste C.) and Rob McAuley ( Playboy ), 1970-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
      With "The Noose," poem, typescript
    - Squire, John Collings, Sir, [1920] March 21 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Taylor, Robert, 1967 April 18 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Tiller, Terence, 1950, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Todd, Ruthven, 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Watson, Francis, 1958, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Weltmann, Lutz, 1952 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      About The Nazarene Gospel Restored
    - Unidentified, [1925]-1972 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Writings
    Autograph manuscripts, unless otherwise noted
    Related Materials
    See also: writings accompanying letters in Correspondence series
    - "All Who Fell Short of Love" (poem), [circa 1960] (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - "The Corner-Knot" (poem), [1926] (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - "A Dark Lady" (poem), [circa 1928] (Box 4, Folder 71)
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified recipient, about the poem
    - "The Demon" (poem). Typescript, signed, with autograph manuscript revisions, [1956] (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - "The Haunted House" (poem; published in Mock Beggar Hall ), [1924] (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - "A History Of Peace" (poem), [circa 1928] (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - The Pier-Glass (collection of poems). Autograph manuscript and typescript, [1921] (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - "Suavia gravioia" (collection of poems), 1925 Christmas (Box 4, Folder 76)
      Laid in: autograph letter, signed, to Siegried Sassoon, presenting the manuscript, undated
    - "Talk on Books" (radio presentation for the BBC), [1924] September (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - "To Boys & Girls" (poem), 1956 March 20 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - "Why Read Poetry?" (essay). Conclusion, revised, [circa 1928] (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Other Papers
    - "The Classics and the Man of Letters" ( Arion questionnaire, completed in autograph manuscript by Graves), [circa 1960] (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Invitation to a memorial service for Graves at the Royal Academy of Arts, London, 1986 January 22, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      Addressed to the director of the Humanities Research Center, University of Texas
      Printed by New Seizin Press, Deià
    - Photograph of Graves in Palma de Mallorca, Spain, [1934] (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Photograph of Graves and his daughter Jenny, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      Inscribed to an unidentified recipient
    - Promotional photographs of Graves, with mimeograph press releases from Doubleday and Company, Inc., undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Reproduction of a photograph of Graves (newspaper clipping), undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Reproduction of a drawing of Graves possibly by Eric Kennington (photograph), undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 86)
      Inscribed to Siegfried Sassoon, 1926, "New Year"
    - Storage box owned by a literary agent of Graves, undated (Box 6, Folder 87)
      Accompanied by a key
- September 2002 Acquisition Addition, 1917-1981, undated; 1.84; (4 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Armbruster, C. H. (Carl Hubert) (with letter from Armbruster), 1947 October 10-14 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Cape, Jonathan, 1929 December 30 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Cassell & Company, 1968 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Sanders, Frank (envelope only), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Sanders, Frank (from Amalie von Ranke Graves and Alfred Perceval Graves), 1929, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Sassoon, Siegfried, 1923 Christmas (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - [Stolt?], Raymond T., 1929 November 30 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      Removed from Good-bye to All That
    - [Turgen?], Elliot, 1966 December 17 (Box 7, Folder 95)
      Removed from Hebrew Myths: the Book of Genesis
    - Unidentified, 1967 August 6 (Box 7, Folder 96)
      removed from proofs of The Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam
    - Unidentified (From Nancy Cunard), no year March 26 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      Removed from Ten Poems More
    - Unidentified (from Beryl Graves), no year October 12 (Box 7, Folder 98)
      Removed from New Collected Poems
    - Unidentified (from Laura (Riding) Jackson), 1933 January 12 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Writings
    - An Ancient Castle (novel). Drafts, proofs, and related correspondence, 1980-1981, undated; 4 (Box 7, Folder 100-103)
    - Books about Graves (reviews, drafts, by an unidentified author), undated (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Other Papers
    - Photograph of Graves in uniform of Royal Welsh Fusiliers, [1917] (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Photograph of Graves, undated (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Frame, fragment, from unidentified photograph, undated (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Sassoon, Siegfried. Caricature of Graves (watercolor), [1926] (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Exhibit labels for "Robert Graves: A Centennial Exhibition," curated by Reese at the Grolier Club, 1995, undated; 3 (Box 7, Folder 109-111)
    - Exhibit labels for "Robert Graves: A Centennial Exhibition," curated by Reese at the Grolier Club, 1995, 8 (Box 8, Folder 112-119)
    - Exhibit labels for "Robert Graves: A Centennial Exhibition," curated by Reese at the Grolier Club, 1995 (Box 8a (Oversize), Folder 119a)
- March 2010 Acquisition, 1925-1972, undated; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Graves to Edith M. Scott, 1946 February 22 (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from unidentified to "Helen," about Graves, with related notes, 1972 April 17 (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - Notes by Graves, undated (Box 9, Folder 122)
  - Clippings by and about Graves, 1925-1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Richards, Frank. Old Soldier Sahib (memoir). Galley proof, [1936] (Box 9, Folder 124)
- Other Acquisitions, 1924-1934, undated; 6
  - Ernest Benn Ltd. Printed advance copy announcement for The English Ballad, undated (Box 9, Folder 125)
    Removed from The English Ballad (call number 2007 1198)
  - Graves, Robert. Autograph manuscript note, signed, to Siegfried Sassoon, undated (Box 9, Folder 126)
    Removed from Poems (1914-27) (call number 2007 1121)
  - Jonathan Cape (Firm). Printed advance copy announcement for But it Still Goes On, undated (Box 9, Folder 127)
    Removed from But it Still Goes On (call number 2007 1257)
  - Secker, Martin. Typed letter, signed, to Robert Graves, 1924 July 18 (Box 9, Folder 128)
    Removed from Deyá: a Portfolio of Five Poems and Lithographs (call number 2008 Folio 79)
  - Serendipity Books (Firm). Manuscript receipt, undated (Box 9, Folder 129)
    Removed from Poems 1965-1968 (call number 2008 881)
  - Unidentified. Christmas card sent to Hester and Siegfried Sassoon, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 130)
    Removed from Poems (1914-1926) (call number 2007 1118)
  - Graves, Robert. Autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified recipient, no year February 28 (Box 9, Folder 131)